<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-macedir-entity-attribute-00.xml"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <!---->

    <title abbrev="Entity Category">The Entity Category SAML Entity Metadata
    Attribute Type</title>

    <author fullname="Leif Johansson" initials="L." surname="Johansson">
      <organization abbrev="NDN">NORDUNet</organization>

      <address>
        <email>leifj@sunet.se</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="26" month="March" year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a SAML entity attribute which can be used to
      assign category membership semantics to an entity.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction and Motivation">
      <t>This document describes an attribute for use with the EntityAttribute
      extension to SAML metadata (denoted "entity category attribute" below).
      The entity category attribute is used to denote the type or category of
      the SAML entity with which the attribute is associated.</t>

      <t>The category of an entity MAY be used to provision policy for release
      of attributes from an Identity Provider but other uses are also possible.
      This document only specifies syntax and semantics for the attribute, it
      does not specify a controlled vocabulary for the attribute values. It is
      expected that other specifications will provide management and discovery
      of the values of the entity category attribute.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Syntax">
      <t>When asserted in SAML metadata the entity category attribute MUST be
      represented using an Attribute element with @NameFormat
      urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri and @Name
      http://macedir.org/entity-category. The entity category attribute MAY
      contain multiple AttributeValue elements. A single EntityAttributes
      element MUST NOT contain multiple separate Attribute elements for the
      same attribute type and instead such cases MUST be represented as
      mutiple AttributeValue elements.</t>

      <t>Each AttributeValue element MUST contain a URI. The URI provides a
      unique identifier of the entity category. This document does not specify
      how such values are discovered but future versions of this specification
      may reference or establish a registry for such values.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Semantics">
      <t>By associating an entity category attribute with a SAML metadata
      entity the publisher of that metdata attests to the fact that according
      to the publisher the SAML metadata entity has the properties and
      semantics associated with each of the attribute values.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Example">
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[<EntityDescriptor entityID="https://foo.example.com">
  <Extensions>
    <EntityAttributes>
      <Attribute 
         NameFormat="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri"
         Name="http://macedir.org/entity-category">
        <AttributeValue>urn:oid:4.7.1.1</AttributeValue>
        <AttributeValue>https://f.example.org/foo</AttributeValue>
      </Attribute>
    </EntityAttributes>
  </Extensions>
</EntityDescriptor>]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This work has been a collaborative effort within the REFEDS and MACE-Dir
        communities. Special thanks to (in no particular order):<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>RL 'Bob' Morgan</t>

          <t>Ken Klingenstein</t>

          <t>Keith Hazelton</t>

          <t>Steven Olshansky</t>

          <t>Mikael Linden</t>

          <t>Nicole Harris</t>

          <t>Ian A. Young</t>

          <t>Tom Scavo</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD - basically we need to talk about the importance of keeping FOP
      control over the attribute here.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119.xml'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
