<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<rfc number="8409" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="independent" category="info">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Entity Category">
      The Entity Category Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) Attribute&nbsp;Types
    </title>

<!-- [rfced] For readability, would you like to update the title as
follows or otherwise?

Original:
The Entity Category SAML Attribute Types

Current:
The Entity Category Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) Attribute Types

Perhaps:
Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) Attributes for Entity Category
-->

    <author initials="I.A." fullname="Ian A. Young" surname="Young" role="editor">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ian@iay.org.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Leif Johansson" initials="L." surname="Johansson">
      <organization>SUNET</organization>
      <address>
        <email>leifj@sunet.se</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Scott Cantor" initials="S." surname="Cantor">
      <organization>Shibboleth Consortium</organization>
      <address>
        <email>cantor.2@osu.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2018"/>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
the title) for use on https://www.rfc-editor.org/search.
-->

<keyword>example</keyword>


    <abstract>

<!-- [rfced] For clarity, may we update this sentence in
the abstract as follows or otherwise?

Original
   This document describes a SAML entity attribute which can be used to
   assign category membership semantics to an entity, and a second
   attribute for use in claiming interoperation with or support for
   entities in such categories.

Perhaps
   This document describes two SAML entity attributes: one that can be
   used to assign category membership semantics to an entity and another
   for use in claiming interoperation with or support for
   entities in such categories.

Or
   This document describes two SAML attributes: the "entity category
   attribute", which can be used to assign category membership semantics to an
   entity, and the "entity category support attribute", which can be used in
   claiming interoperation with or support for entities in such categories.
-->
      <t>
        This document describes a Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) entity attribute that can be used to
        assign category membership semantics to an entity and a second attribute
        for use in claiming interoperation with or support for entities in such categories.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document is a product of the working group process of the
	Research and Education Federations group (REFEDS).
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
      <t>
        This document describes a SAML attribute referred to here as the
	"entity category attribute".
        Values of this attribute represent entity types
        or categories. When used with the
        <xref target="SAML2MetadataAttr">SAML V2.0 Metadata Extension for Entity Attributes</xref>,
        each such entity category attribute value represents a claim that the entity thus labeled
        meets the requirements of, and is asserted to be a member of, the indicated category.
      </t>

      <t>
        These category membership claims MAY be used by a relying party to provision policy
        for release of attributes from an identity provider, to influence user interface decisions
        such as those related to identity provider discovery, or for any other purpose.
        In general, the intended uses of any claim of membership in a given category will
        depend on the details of the category's definition and will often be included as
        part of that definition.
      </t>

      <t>
        Entity category attribute values are URIs; therefore, this document does not specify a
        controlled vocabulary for assigning entity category values.  Category URIs may be defined
        by any appropriate authority without any requirement for central registration.  It is anticipated that
        other specifications may provide management and discovery mechanisms for entity category
        attribute values.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document also describes a SAML attribute referred to here as the
	"entity category support attribute". This attribute
        contains URI values that represent claims that an entity supports and/or interoperates with
        entities in a given category or categories. These values, defined in conjunction with
        specific entity category values, provide entities in a category with the means to identify
        peer entities that wish to interact with them in a fashion described by the category specification.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document does not specify any values for either the entity category attribute
        or the entity category support attribute.
      </t>

      <section title="REFEDS Document Process">
        <t>
          The Research and Education Federations group <xref target="REFEDS"/>
          is the voice that articulates the mutual needs of research and education
          identity federations worldwide. It aims to represent the requirements of
          research and education in the ever-growing space of access and identity
          management.
        </t>
        <t>
          From time to time, REFEDS
          will publish a document in the RFC Series.  Such
          documents will be published as part of the Independent Submission
          stream <xref target="RFC4844"/>; however, the REFEDS Working Group
	  sign-off process will
          have been followed for these documents, as described in
          the <xref target="REFEDS.agreement">REFEDS Participant's Agreement</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          This document is a product of the REFEDS Working Group process.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Notation and Conventions">

        <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>


    </section>

    <section title="Entity Category Attribute">
      <section anchor="cat-syntax" title="Syntax">
        <t>
          Entity category attribute values MUST be valid URIs. It is
	  RECOMMENDED that http:-scheme
          or https:-scheme URIs are used; it is further RECOMMENDED that an
	  entity category URI
          resolves to a human-readable document defining the category.
        </t>

        <t>
          Authorities defining entity categories MUST produce a specification of the entity
          category and SHOULD make arrangement for the entity category URI to resolve to the
          specification in human-readable form.
        </t>

        <t>
          Authorities defining entity categories MAY use versioning of entity category URIs where
          appropriate; if versioning is used, each version of the specification of the entity category
          SHOULD clearly indicate the latest version of the entity category URI (and hence of the
          specification).

<!-- [rfced]  May we update "in the case when the specification may be updated"
as follows?

Original
   The specification SHOULD include a description of
   how the authority defining the entity category implements governance
   for the specification in the case when the specification may be
   updated.

Perhaps
   The specification SHOULD include a description of
   how the authority defining the entity category implements governance
   for the specification if the specification is updated.
-->

The specification SHOULD include a description of how the authority
          defining the entity category implements governance for the specification in the case
          when the specification may be updated.
        </t>

        <t>
          When used in SAML metadata or protocol elements, the entity category attribute MUST
          be encoded as a SAML 2.0 Attribute element with @NameFormat urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri
          and @Name http://macedir.org/entity-category.
        </t>

        <t>
          A SAML entity is associated with one or more categories by including the
          Attribute element described here in the entity's metadata through
	  use of the metadata extension defined in
          <xref target="SAML2MetadataAttr"/>. In this extension, the
          Attribute element is contained within an mdattr:EntityAttributes
          element directly contained within an md:Extensions element directly
          contained within the entity's md:EntityDescriptor.
        </t>

        <t>
          The meaning of the entity category attribute is not defined by this specification if it
          appears anywhere else within a metadata instance or within any other XML document.
        </t>

        <t>
          If the entity category attribute Attribute element appears more than once in the
          metadata for an entity, the combined set of associated attribute values SHOULD be
          interpreted by relying parties as if they all appeared within a single Attribute
          element.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="cat-semantics" title="Semantics">
        <t>
          The presence of the entity category attribute within an entity's entity attributes
          represents a series of claims (one for each attribute value) that the entity is
          a member of each named category.  The precise semantics of such a claim depend
          on the definition of the category itself.
        </t>

        <t>
          An entity may be claimed to be a member of more than one category. In this case, the entity
          is claimed to meet the requirements of each category independently unless otherwise
          specified by the category definitions themselves.
        </t>


<!-- [rfced]  Would updating these sentences as follows improve readability
and clarity?

Original
   The definition of the concept of a category is intentionally not
   addressed in this document, in order to leave it as general as
   possible.
...
   The definition of the concept of "support" for a category is
   intentionally not addressed in this document, in order to leave it as
   general as possible.

Perhaps
   This document intentionally does not define "category", in order to
   leave the concept as general as possible.
...
   This document intentionally does not define "support" for a category,
   in order to leave the concept as general as possible.
-->
        <t>
          The definition of the concept of a "category" is intentionally not addressed in this
          document, in order to leave it as general as possible.  However, to be useful,
          category definitions SHOULD include the following as appropriate:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              A definition of the authorities who may validly assert
              membership in the category.  While membership in some categories may be
              self-asserted informally by an entity's owner, others may need to be
              validated by third parties such as the entity's home federation or other
              registrar.
            </t>
            <t>
              A set of criteria by which an entity's membership in the category can be
              objectively assessed.
            </t>
            <t>
              A definition of the processes by which valid authorities
              may determine that an entity meets the category's membership criteria.
            </t>
            <t>
              A description of the anticipated uses for category membership by relying parties.
            </t>
            <t>
              A statement indicating the applicability or otherwise of membership
              of the entity category to different SAML role descriptors and any
              protocol support restrictions that may be relevant.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          Entity categories SHOULD NOT be used to indicate the certification
          status of an entity regarding its conformance to the requirements
          of an identity assurance framework.


<!-- [rfced]  We do not see "extension" used in [SAML2IDAssuranceProfile]. Is
"assurance profiles" or something else intended? Please review and let us
know if any updates are needed.

Original
   The [SAML2IDAssuranceProfile]
   extension SHOULD be used for this purpose.
-->
          The extension defined in
	  <xref target="SAML2IDAssuranceProfile"/> SHOULD be used
          for this purpose.
        </t>

        <t>
          If significant changes are made to a category definition, the new version of
          the category SHOULD be represented by a different category URI
          so that the old and new versions can be distinguished by a relying party. It
          is for this reason that authorities defining entity categories MAY
          employ some form of versioning for entity category URIs. When versioning is
          used, each version of the entity category MUST be treated as a separate URI.
        </t>


<!-- [rfced]  Is "over" correct here? Note that this sentence appears twice in
the document. (We typically see usage of "defined over" as in "defined over"
a set or a range.)

Original
   No ordering relation is defined over entity category value URIs.

Perhaps
   No ordering relation is defined for entity category value URIs.
-->
        <t>
          No ordering relation is defined over entity category value URIs.
          Entity category attribute value URIs MUST be treated as opaque strings
          for the purpose of comparison. In particular, if the specification defining the
          entity category relies on versioning of the entity category URI, a relying
          party MUST NOT assume any particular ordering between different versions of
          the entity category. Any order between versions MUST be spelled out in the
          specification.
        </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Entity Category Example">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[<md:EntityDescriptor xmlns:md="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:metadata"
  entityID="https://service.example.com/entity">
  <md:Extensions>
    <mdattr:EntityAttributes
      xmlns:mdattr="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:metadata:attribute">
      <Attribute xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:assertion"
        NameFormat="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri"
        Name="http://macedir.org/entity-category">
        <AttributeValue
          >http://example.org/category/dog</AttributeValue>
        <AttributeValue>urn:oid:1.3.6.1.4.1.21829</AttributeValue>
      </Attribute>
    </mdattr:EntityAttributes>
  </md:Extensions>
  ...
</md:EntityDescriptor>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Entity Category Support Attribute">
      <section anchor="sup-syntax" title="Syntax">


<!-- [rfced]  The similar sentences below appear in Sections 3.1 and 4.1.
One uses "valid URIs" while the other uses "URIs". Please confirm that
this is correct.

Section 3.1
  Entity category attribute values MUST be valid URIs.

Section 4.1
  Entity category support attribute values MUST be URIs.
-->


        <t>
          Entity category support attribute values MUST be URIs.  It is RECOMMENDED that
          http:-scheme or https:-scheme URLs are used; it is further RECOMMENDED that each
          such value resolves to a human-readable document defining the value's semantics.
          A given entity category value MAY be associated with multiple support values in
          order to allow for multiple forms of support, participation, or interoperation
          with entities in the category. The authority defining the entity category and
          entity category support values MUST clearly describe the relationship between
          (all versions of) the entity category URI and (all versions of) the entity
          category support URIs as applicable in the entity category specification.
        </t>

<!-- [rfced]  We see that http://macedir.org/entity-category redirects to
https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-young-entity-category-07. In addition,
we encountered a "404 Not Found" when trying to open
http://macedir.org/entity-category-support. Please review and let us know
how to update.

Original:
   When used in SAML metadata or protocol elements, the entity category
   attribute MUST be encoded as a SAML 2.0 Attribute element with
   @NameFormat urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri and @Name
   http://macedir.org/entity-category.
...
   The entity category support attribute MUST be encoded as a SAML 2.0
   Attribute element with @NameFormat
   urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri and @Name
   http://macedir.org/entity-category-support.
-->


<!-- [rfced] Another question about this text: would it make sense
to write out the meaning rather than use the "@" convention?
If so, does the text below convey the intended meaning?
(Related question: Is "@registrationAuthority attribute" redundant?
It appears twice in this document.)

Original:
   When used in SAML metadata or protocol elements, the entity category
   attribute MUST be encoded as a SAML 2.0 Attribute element with
   @NameFormat urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri and @Name
   http://macedir.org/entity-category.
...
   The entity category support attribute MUST be encoded as a SAML 2.0
   Attribute element with @NameFormat
   urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri and @Name
   http://macedir.org/entity-category-support.
...
   ...corresponding
   @registrationAuthority attribute as described in
   [SAML2MetadataRPI] section 2.1.1.


Perhaps:
   When used in SAML metadata or protocol elements, the entity category
   attribute MUST be encoded as a SAML 2.0 Attribute element with
   a NameFormat attribute with the value
   urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri and a Name attribute
   with the value http://macedir.org/entity-category.
...
   The entity category support attribute MUST be encoded as a SAML 2.0
   Attribute element with a NameFormat attribute with the value
   urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri and a Name attribute
   with the value http://macedir.org/entity-category-support.
...
   ...corresponding
   registrationAuthority attribute as described in
   Section 2.1.1 of [SAML2MetadataRPI].
-->

        <t>
          The entity category support attribute MUST be encoded as a SAML 2.0 Attribute
          element with @NameFormat urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri and
          @Name http://macedir.org/entity-category-support.
        </t>

        <t>
          Claims that a SAML entity implements support for one or more categories
          are represented by including the Attribute element described here in the entity's metadata
          through use of the metadata extension defined in <xref
	  target="SAML2MetadataAttr"/>.
          In this extension,
          the Attribute element is contained within an mdattr:EntityAttributes
          element directly contained within an md:Extensions element directly
          contained within the entity's md:EntityDescriptor.
        </t>

        <t>
          The meaning of the entity category support attribute is not defined by this
          specification if it appears anywhere else within a metadata instance or within
          any other XML document.
        </t>

        <t>
          If the entity category support attribute Attribute element appears more than once in the
          metadata for an entity, the combined set of associated attribute values SHOULD be
          interpreted by relying parties as if they all appeared within a single Attribute
          element.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sup-semantics" title="Semantics">
        <t>
          The presence of the entity category support attribute within an entity's entity
          attributes represents a series of claims (one for each attribute
          value) that the entity supports peer entities in a category in a particular
          fashion. The precise semantics of such a claim depend on the definition of the
          category support identifier itself.
          Category support claims will often be defined to be self-asserted.
        </t>

        <t>
          An entity may be claimed to support more than one category. In this case, the entity
          is claimed to meet the support requirements of each category independently unless otherwise
          specified by the category definitions themselves.
        </t>

        <t>
          The definition of the concept of "support" for a category is intentionally not
          addressed in this document, in order to leave it as general as possible.  It is
          assumed that entity category definitions MAY define one or more support values
          signifying particular definitions for "support" by peers as motivated by use
          cases arising from the definition of the category itself.
        </t>

        <t>
          A common case is expected to be the definition of a single support value
          whose URI is identical to that defined for the category itself.
        </t>

        <t>
          If significant changes are made to a category support definition, the new version
          SHOULD be represented by a different category support URI so that the old and new
          versions can be distinguished by a relying party. It is for this reason that
          authorities defining entity categories support MAY employ some form of versioning.
          When versioning is used, each version of the entity category support
	  URI MUST be treated
          as a separate URI.
        </t>

<!-- [rfced]  The similar sentences below appear in Sections 3.2 and
4.2. Should the sentence in Section 4.2 refer to "entity category
support" rather than "entity category"?

Section 3.2
   No ordering relation is defined over entity category value URIs.

Section 4.2
   No ordering relation is defined over entity category URIs.
-->

        <t>
          No ordering relation is defined over entity category URIs.
          Entity category attribute support value URIs MUST be treated as opaque strings
          for the purpose of comparison. In particular, if the specification defining the
          entity category support values relies on versioning, a relying
          party MUST NOT assume any particular ordering between different versions of
          the entity category support URI. Any order between versions MUST be spelled
          out in the specification.
        </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Entity Category Support Example">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[<md:EntityDescriptor xmlns:md="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:metadata"
  entityID="https://idp.example.edu/entity">
  <md:Extensions>
    <mdattr:EntityAttributes
      xmlns:mdattr="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:metadata:attribute">
      <Attribute xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:assertion"
        NameFormat="urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:2.0:attrname-format:uri"
        Name="http://macedir.org/entity-category-support">
        <AttributeValue
          >http://example.org/category/dog/basic</AttributeValue>
        <AttributeValue
          >http://example.org/category/dog/advanced</AttributeValue>
        <AttributeValue>urn:oid:1.3.6.1.4.1.21829</AttributeValue>
      </Attribute>
    </mdattr:EntityAttributes>
  </md:Extensions>
  ...
</md:EntityDescriptor>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document has no IANA actions.
</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The presence of the entity category attribute within an entity's entity attributes
        represents a series of claims (one for each attribute value) that the entity is
        a member of the named categories.  Before accepting and acting on such claims, any
        relying party needs to establish, at a level of assurance sufficient for the
        intended use, a chain of trust concluding that the claim is justified.
      </t>

      <t>
        Some of the elements in such a chain of trust might include:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            The integrity of the metadata delivered to the relying party,
	    for
	    example, as
            assured by a digital signature.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the entity category attribute is carried within a signed assertion, the assertion
            itself must be evaluated.
          </t>
          <t>
            The policies and procedures of the immediate source of the metadata,
            in particular, any procedures the immediate source has with regard to aggregation
            of metadata from other sources.
          </t>
          <t>
            The policies and procedures implemented by agents along the publication path from
            the original metadata registrar. This may be determined by examination of
            the published procedures of each agent in turn or may be simplified if the
            entity metadata includes publication path metadata in mdrpi:PublicationPath
            elements as described in Section 2.3.1 of
            <xref target="SAML2MetadataRPI"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The policies and procedures implemented by the original metadata registrar.
            The registrar's identity may be known implicitly or may be determined
            from the entity metadata if it includes an mdrpi:RegistrationInfo element
            and corresponding @registrationAuthority attribute as described in
	    Section 2.1.1 of
            <xref target="SAML2MetadataRPI"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The definition of the category itself, in particular, any
	    statements it makes about
            whether membership of the category may be self-asserted or may
	    only be asserted
            by particular authorities.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Although entity category support attribute values will often be defined as self-asserted
        claims by the containing entity, the provenance of the metadata remains
        relevant to a relying party's decision to accept a claim of support as legitimate,
        and the specific definition of a support claim will influence the assurance
        required to act on it.
      </t>

      <t>
        The conclusion that a claim of category membership or support is justified and
        should be acted upon may require a determination of the origin of the claim.
        This may not be necessary if the immediate source of the metadata is trusted to such
        an extent that the trust calculation is essentially delegated to it.
      </t>

      <t>
        In many cases, a claim will be included in an entity's metadata by the
        original metadata registrar on behalf of the entity's owner, and the mdrpi:RegistrationInfo
        element's @registrationAuthority attribute is available to carry the registrar's identity.
        However, any agent that is part of the chain of custody between the original registrar and the final
        relying party may have added, removed, or transformed claims according to local policy.
        For example, an agent charged with redistributing metadata may remove claims it regards
        as untrustworthy or add others that were not already present if they have value to
        its intended audience.
      </t>

    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>


<!-- [rfced]  Please note that we updated the URLs for the following
references to point directly to the document being referenced.
Please let us know if you prefer otherwise.

Original:
   [SAML2MetadataAttr]
              Cantor, S., Ed., "SAML V2.0 Metadata Extension for Entity
              Attributes", August 2009,
              <http://wiki.oasis-open.org/security/SAML2MetadataAttr>.

   [SAML2MetadataRPI]
              La Joie, C., Ed., "SAML V2.0 Metadata Extensions for
              Registration and Publication Information Version 1.0",
              April 2012,
              <http://wiki.oasis-open.org/security/SAML2MetadataDRI>.

   [SAML2IDAssuranceProfile]
              Morgan, RL., Ed., Madsen, P., Ed., and S. Cantor, Ed.,
              "SAML V2.0 Identity Assurance Profiles Version 1.0",
              November 2010, <https://wiki.oasis-open.org/security/
              SAML2IDAssuranceProfile>.

Current:
(Side note: the placement of line breaks in the URLs will be
improved before final publication.)

   [SAML2MetadataAttr]
              Cantor, S., Ed., "SAML V2.0 Metadata Extension for Entity
              Attributes Version 1.0", August 2009, <http://docs.oasis-
              open.org/security/saml/Post2.0/
              sstc-metadata-attr-cs-01.html>.

   [SAML2MetadataRPI]
              La Joie, C., Ed., "SAML V2.0 Metadata Extensions for
              Registration and Publication Information Version 1.0",
              April 2012, <http://docs.oasis-
              open.org/security/saml/Post2.0/saml-metadata-
              rpi/v1.0/cs01/saml-metadata-rpi-v1.0-cs01.html>.

   [SAML2IDAssuranceProfile]
              Morgan, RL., Ed., Madsen, P., Ed., and S. Cantor, Ed.,
              "SAML V2.0 Identity Assurance Profiles Version 1.0",
              November 2010, <http://docs.oasis-
              open.org/security/saml/Post2.0/
              sstc-saml-assurance-profile-cs-01.html>.

  [12] RESOLVED: changed references to be to .pdf versions

-->
      <reference anchor="SAML2MetadataAttr"
        target="http://docs.oasis-open.org/security/saml/Post2.0/sstc-metadata-attr-cs-01.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>SAML V2.0 Metadata Extension for Entity Attributes Version 1.0</title>
          <author fullname="Scott Cantor" role="editor" initials="S." surname="Cantor"/>
          <date day="3" month="August" year="2009"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SAML2MetadataRPI"
        target="http://docs.oasis-open.org/security/saml/Post2.0/saml-metadata-rpi/v1.0/cs01/saml-metadata-rpi-v1.0-cs01.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>SAML V2.0 Metadata Extensions for Registration and Publication Information Version 1.0</title>
          <author surname="La Joie" initials="C." role="editor" fullname="Chad La Joie"/>
          <date day="3" month="April" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4844"?>


      <reference anchor="REFEDS" target="http://www.refeds.org/">
        <front>
          <title>Research and Education Federations Group (REFEDS)</title>
          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="REFEDS.agreement" target="https://refeds.org/about/refeds-participants-agreement">
        <front>
          <title>REFEDS Participant's Agreement</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Research and Education Federations</organization>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SAML2IDAssuranceProfile"
        target="http://docs.oasis-open.org/security/saml/Post2.0/sstc-saml-assurance-profile-cs-01.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>SAML V2.0 Identity Assurance Profiles Version 1.0</title>
          <author fullname='RL "Bob" Morgan' role="editor" initials="RL" surname="Morgan"/>
          <author fullname="Paul Madsen" role="editor" initials="P" surname="Madsen"/>
          <author fullname="Scott Cantor" role="editor" initials="S." surname="Cantor"/>
          <date day="5" month="November" year="2010"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>
        This work has been a collaborative effort within the REFEDS and MACE-Dir
        communities. Special thanks to the following individuals (in no particular order):
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>RL 'Bob' Morgan</t>

          <t>Ken Klingenstein</t>

          <t>Keith Hazelton</t>

          <t>Steven Olshansky</t>

          <t>Mikael Linden</t>

          <t>Nicole Harris</t>

          <t>Tom Scavo</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>


<!-- [rfced]  Terminology

a) Should the expansion for REFEDS include the word "group"? In other words,
should the expansion be "Research and Education Federations (REFEDS)" or
as "Research and Education Federations group (REFEDS)"? We see it appears
both ways in this document and on https://refeds.org/ (main page vs.
Participant's Agreement).


b) We see the following forms used in the document. Should these be
consistent? If so, please let us know which form is preferred. Alternately,
would it improve readability to recast these to read "value of the entity
category attribute" and "value of the entity category support attribute?

entity category value vs. entity category attribute value

entity category support value vs. entity category support attribute value


c) We see the following forms used for URIs in this document. Should these be
consistent? If so, please let us know which form is preferred.

entity category URI
category URI
entity category value URI
entity category attribute value URI

entity category support URI
category support URI
attribute support value URI
entity category attribute support value URI


d) We find "entity category attribute Attribute element" and "entity category
support attribute Attribute element" difficult to read in these sentences. How
can we recast these for clarity?

Original
   If the entity category attribute Attribute element appears more than
   once in the metadata for an entity, the combined set of associated
   attribute values SHOULD be interpreted by relying parties as if they
   all appeared within a single Attribute element.
...
   If the entity category support attribute Attribute element appears
   more than once in the metadata for an entity, the combined set of
   associated attribute values SHOULD be interpreted by relying parties
   as if they all appeared within a single Attribute element.
-->

  </back>
</rfc>
